בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is דף י. Daf Yud.
We pick up in the middle of ט"ו ע"ב. Tet Vav Bet.
We'll start from the גמרא Gemara right after the משנה. Mishna. There's
a debate of רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda and רבי מאיר Reb Meir
whether if a blind person had committed murder, whether they are, whether
they would go into exile, where רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda said he
would not and רבי מאיר Reb Meir said he would. So you
could have said that this debate might have to do with like
degree of responsibility, you know, I really don't know the story about
how much in the ancient world, you know, or like now, you
know, you have seeing eye dogs and, you know, they have sticks
and, you know, like blind people can navigate pretty well. And
so I don't know, you know, you could have made it a
question about like how much do we assume that you should, you
know, is able to be fully aware of the surroundings and degree
of responsibility, but the גמרא Gemara makes it an issue based on
how to interpret the verses. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: בלא ראות. belo re'ot. So it
says that you fall, you know, an accident occurred but you didn't
see the guy and therefore this thing occurred and he got killed.
So which means implicitly that you could have seen the guy, okay?
פרט לסומא, Prat l'suma, that excludes a blind person who there was
no way he could have seen him. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Reb
Yehuda. So although it's based on a verse, you could understand the
point I'm saying that it's an issue of responsibility, you know, how
much, you know, is it, you know, should he have, you know,
could we have put the responsibility on him that he could have
been more aware. רבי מאיר אומר: Reb Meir omer: בלא ראות, belo
re'ot, לרבות את הסומא. l'rabbot et hasuma. No, the opposite. בלא ראות
Belo re'ot means even somebody who can't see, even a blind person,
not that you could have seen. So מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? mai
ta'ama de-Reb Yehuda? What's the reason of רבי יהודה? Reb Yehuda? And
if anything, the reason of רבי מאיר Reb Meir needs a little
more explanation. רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda is a reasonable read of the
verse. דכתיב, De-khitiv, because it says, ואשר יבא את רעהו ביער, v'asher
yavo et re'ehu baya'ar, somebody who comes with his friend into the
forest.
So anybody who comes with his friend, אפילו סומא, afilu suma, even
a blind person, אף בלא ראות, af belo re'ot, and then it
says and it happened without seeing him, implying he could have seen
him, מיעטה, mi'ata,
so that excludes a blind person, fine, like we said. רבי מאיר:
Reb Meir: בלא ראות, belo re'ot, למעט, l'ma'et, למעט, l'ma'et,
it's true, I agree, בלא ראות belo re'ot is coming to exclude
certain
people, presumably somebody who anyway couldn't have seen. So if I just
stopped there, I'd agree with you, רבי יהודה. Reb Yehuda. But
בבלי דעת, bivli da'at, there's another verse that says and it happened
without awareness. So that's also למעט, l'ma'et, that also comes to exclude,
implying somebody that could have been aware as opposed to somebody who
couldn't have been aware. So one thing says somebody who could have
seen and the other says somebody who could have been aware. So
there's two verses that are seemingly to shrink the circle to be
exclusionary. And then you have the classic rabbinic move, you know, this
bizarre move, הוי מיעוט אחר מיעוט ואין מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא לרבות.
havi mi'ut achar mi'ut ve-ein mi'ut achar mi'ut ela l'rabbot.
So since there's two things which exclude a blind person, you know,
one of them is obviously coming therefore to be inclusive. I mean
not one, therefore the net effect of them is to include rather
than to exclude. Okay, since both of those things point to exclude
a blind person, the result is that we include. Of course, the
obvious question is, then why did you need either of those words?
Just don't say anything. Anyway, it's a very bizarre position, you know,
hermeneutics, the position might not be bizarre, but the hermeneutics is. רבי
יהודה: Reb Yehuda: בבלי דעת, bivli da'at, now what does רבי יהודה
Reb Yehuda do with the word בבלי דעת? bivli da'at?
So he says, you know, it's because if he's not using it
to exclude a blind person, he's already excluded a blind person, so
פרט למתכוין, prat l'mitkaven, to exclude if it's intentional. Now obviously not
intentional intentional, then you don't need a פסוק, pasuk, but the intentional
is, which is what the גמרא Gemara says, so you know when
you try, it means a case for example somebody tried to kill
an animal and it turned out to be a person or something
of that nature, okay? Or okay. Now,
לההוא דאתא, l'hahu d'ata, fine. So that's the debate about a blind
person. Moving on, רבי יוסי אומר השונא נהרג. Reb Yossi omer hasoné
neherag. Now רבי יוסי Reb Yossi says, so the first משנה Mishna
said שונא soné isn't גולה, goleh, because it says והוא לא שונא
לו מתמול שלשום, ve-hu lo soneh lo mitmol shilshom, right? And presumably
the logic is, again, if we don't want to just make it
based on the פסוק, pasuk, the logic is that, you know, why?
I mean if the שונא soné then we're concerned that maybe it
was intentional. So if that's our concern, that maybe it was intentional,
all the more reason he should be punished, he shouldn't get off
scot-free. You know, but this is the general, you know, assumption of
the גמרא, Gemara, that if you're, if you're too guilty, you don't
get גלות galus either. גלות Galus is only for somebody that's in
that sweet spot of having the right level of responsibility. If you're
too, if it's you're too much not responsible, you don't get גלות
galus because you don't deserve גלות. galus. And if you're too, you
know, if you're too negligent or too, too guilty, we might not
be able to execute the guy, but also we're not going to
give him the כפרה kapara of גלות. galus. So presumably that's the
reason that the שונא soné doesn't get גלות. galus. We suspect that
it might not have just been an accident, okay? So we can't
execute the guy, but also we're not going to give him גלות.
galus. All right, so that's the position of the משנה. Mishna. But
then רבי שמעון Reb Shimon says, so השונא, hasoné, רבי יוסי Reb
Yossi says השונא נהרג, hasoné neherag, you know, that he would actually
be executed. Now, of course, the question is, because presumably we assume
it was intended. intentional. Of course, the funny thing is, fine, we
assume it was intentional, but where was that like the התראה? Hasro'ah?
Where was the warning? Like who else could have seen this guy,
his sworn enemy and whoops accidentally had an accident and ran over
the guy, you know, was total accident or the shovel broke, you
know whatever the the the bucket broke, right? So they they witnessed
it but and they might assume that he's making it look like
an accident and it was intentional. And even if we can somehow
say that that's enough the presumption is strong enough that we really
in court would believe it to be the case, you're still technically
missing the issue of התראה. Hasro'ah. So what about that? So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. והלא לא התרו בו, V'ho
lo atru bey, but they didn't give him התראה. Hasro'ah. מתניתין רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה היא. Masnisin Rib Yose b'Rib Yehuda hee. No, our
משנה Mishna is going like רבי יוסי, Rib Yose, it's not just
רבי יוסי, Rib Yose, it's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rib Yose b'Rib
Yehuda. דתניא, D'tanya, it's taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה אומר, Rib Yose b'Rib Yehuda omer, חבר אינו צריך התראה. Chaver
aino tzarich hasro'ah. A somebody who is knowledgeable in the law does
not need warning. לפי שלא ניתנה התראה אלא להבחין בין שוגג למזיד.
Lefi shelo nitna hasro'ah elah l'havchin bein shogeg l'mayzid. התראה Hasro'ah is
coming normal, you know, התראה Hasro'ah is coming to to only
to ensure that the guy is doing it intentionally. That a, he's
intent intending to do his act and b, that he's doing it
knowing that it's forbidden. That's why you need the חבר. Chaver. The
חבר Chaver is somebody who's knows the law, obviously knows it's forbidden.
So he does not need warning. So normally, why do we assume
you need התראה? Hasro'ah? One is because maybe yes you want to
ensure that the person is aware and does know the consequence. But
also התראה Hasro'ah creates a reality that the person is doing it
in direct defiance and rejection of the authority and even a way
the גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין Sanhedrin spoke about התיר עצמו למיתה. Hitir
atzmo l'misa. He's even accepting upon himself the consequences of his act
and therefore that's giving license for the בית דין Beis Din to
execute him. Okay? So התראה Hasro'ah does more than just determine that
a person is willful and intentional and intentionally breaking the law. But
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rib Yose b'Rib Yehuda says no that's all
you need it to do is just know that he's intending. And
therefore if the guy is a חבר, Chaver, so he knows it's
against the law, and b, he's a שונא, Sonay, so therefore we
can assume that he's not doing it by accident, he's doing it
willingly. The combination of those two let us execute this guy without
warning. Now again I have to tell you I still find that
pretty surprising. Like sometimes even sworn enemies have accidents, you know? And
like, okay, so could the guy be really devious and make it
look like an accident and it really be intentional? Sure. But like
is that enough of a basis to execute somebody? You know you
could think about a range of cases, right? You could think about
a cases where you know and we I would say we should
like maybe have to look at the circumstances, right? Some circumstances you
know there's enough that makes us think he's it only looks like
an accident, it really was, others maybe it really was. So I
don't know, I don't know the answer. I would hope that רבי
יוסי Rib Yose would actually say that you would actually take into
account the context and the circumstances and if in the court's best
judgment it was intentional even though it looks like an accident, we
would. But even that's an interesting question. Like since when do we,
you know, do something based on the fact that you know this
is our presumption? It gets to a whole discussion about whether you
can execute based on רוב. Rov. Like we presume that this is
somebody's father so therefore we'll execute him if he like you know
smote his father whatever. You know there's a lot of presumptions we
work with in a court of law. The גמרא Gemara uses this
and sometimes on the basis of those presumptions we will execute somebody.
Okay? But it's still a little bit different if there's a presumption
that preceded the case. For last twenty years we've been assuming that
this is this man's father. So now he comes along and he
hits him and he makes a wound and he was warned or
whatever, so we're going to just work with that assumption and therefore
say he did a capital crime and execute him. It's a little
different if in the case itself we don't know what happened and
because of our best judgment call it was intentional and now we're
going to execute. Like normally you assume no, isn't that why the
whole need for witnesses and for you know absolute and clear and
clear knowledge and not just having presumptions factor into it? So I
really don't know the answer. I mean to me the התראה Hasro'ah
is not the is not what bothers me as much as how
we can how we just assume that it was intentional.
He still had to prove this guy was also a שונא. Sonay.
How do you prove that? You know?
That's also an interest but that could have been the presumption that
preceded the case. You're right.
No, but you need to know.
Right. How do you define that?
Oh maybe just because they didn't see each other.
Right. Right, that's true too. Alright, so anyway that's a very curious
thing but that's more of a סנהדרין Sanhedrin discussion than a מכות
Makkos discussion.
They don't have witnesses to the whole act, so wouldn't the witnesses
have some sense of?
Right, but that would be the question, like are the witnesses saying
we saw him intentionally do it? Then you don't need him to
be a שונא, Sonay, then you don't need right? So are you
know un you know do
or are we saying that what the witnesses are saying was like
yeah, we saw the rope break and whatever and it was a
little suspicious because of x, y, and z, but we don't know
for sure whether it was intentional, right? So you know, anyway.
Did he give an impression of this situation with they?
No,
I know but we don't use that, no not normally, no. Alright,
anyway. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי שמעון אומר
יש שונא גולה. Rib Shimon omer yesh sonay goleh. So now back
to גלות. Goloss. רבי שמעון Rib Shimon says sometimes yes sometimes no.
So So כל שיכול לומר לדעת הרג, kol sheyachol lomar ladaat harag,
if there's a basis. Now, the nice thing about רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon is יכול לומר yachol lomar that he actually deals with the
fact that we have suspicions, but we don't know for sure. If
there's a reason to say that it was intentional,
he wouldn't be גולה goleh to גלות. golus. If it seems to
say, if the indications are that it was not intentional, he would.
So can you give us a little more specifics? So the גמרא
Gemara says תניא, tanya, we're talking about a ברייתא.
Baraisa. Would you say the ניקילום nikillum or would you say in
that?
No, it's about going to גלות. golus.
No, about לדעת. ladaat.
No, because there's still בהתראה, behatra'ah, and that speaks to, he's right.
לדעת ladaat don't go and kill him.
Basically, yup. תניא כיצד אמר רבי שמעון יש שונה גולה ויש שונה
שאינו גולה. tanya keitzad amar Rabbi Shimon yesh shoneh goleh veyesh shoneh
she'eino goleh. נפסק nifsak גולה, goleh, נשמט nishmat אינו גולה. eino goleh.
Okay, so if the rope broke, then he would
go into גלות. golus. If it slipped out of his hands, he
would not. You sort of understand that, right? Because whoops, slipped out
of my hands, that's a reason to say, you know, now again,
maybe, maybe like it's not like we saw anything in the slipping
itself that indicated it was intentional, but the very fact that that
that was the case, it slipped and he was a שונא, soneh,
opens up the possibility.
You know, יכול לומר, yachol lomar, right, opens it up. Maybe it's
only a fifty-fifty possibility. It doesn't matter, it makes it a reasonable
possibility, even if not more likely than others. You know, whereas if
it's נפסק, nifsak, the most likely possibility is that it was an
accident. Although, of course, you could imagine the guy goes beforehand and
he, you know, whittled down the rope or something. Okay.
Okay, והתניא, vehatanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא Baraisa רבי שמעון
אומר לעולם אינו גולה עד שישמט מחלצו מידו? Rabbi Shimon omer le'olam
eino goleh ad sheyishamat machlatzo miyado? He never goes into גלות golus
unless the
מחלצו... machlatzo... but she said מחצלו, machtzalo, whatever, that's the, the tool
that's used for tarring the roof, the מעגיל ma'agil or something. So
he never goes into גלות golus unless it actually slips. So it's
the exact opposite. It would seem that if it
breaks he does go into גלות golus and if it slips he
does not go into גלות. golus. Right? So, I'm sorry, I got
that wrong. No, the first one said that if it's, now I'm
confused. It's the איפכא. ipcha. It's the opposite, right? So
the first thing is like here, we'll draw the hands, and that's
the, and here's the rope. Okay, and that's the, that's the whatever,
נשמט. nishmat. Okay. Whoops, haha. Whoops.
Okay, so alright, so that's that case. Okay, and then the other
one is, so that, that's the case where he's...
Are you erasing the עיר מקלט? ir miklat? Whoops. Okay.
Whoops.
Wait a minute, did she get to the עיר מקלט? ir miklat?
I thought she, okay. She drew the pictures first. Oh, I see.
I see. He's on the right. Okay. Okay, here's this one. Okay,
and this is, okay, and that's נפסק. nifsak. Okay, so what we
said is that this, he goes into, he's גולה goleh because that's
a reasonable by mistake, and that's אינו גולה eino goleh because it
looks like it's, there's a reasonable possibility that that was not really
an accident. Okay, and so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, so
where were we? תניא, tanya, okay, והתניא רבי שמעון אומר לעולם אינו
גולה עד שישמט מחצלו מידו, vehatanya Rabbi Shimon omer le'olam eino goleh
ad sheyishamat machtzalo miyado,
that only this case he goes into גלות golus and not this,
so it's the exact opposite, or assume the מחצלו machtzalo is the
same as whatever the bucket or whatever, effectively the same. קשיא נפסק
אנפסק קשיא נשמט אנשמט. kashya nifsak anifsak kashya nishmat anishmat. It's a
direct mirror image of the other case. Okay. נפסק אנפסק לא קשיא
הא באוהב הא בשונא. nifsak anifsak lo kashya ha b'ohev ha b'soneh.
נשמט אנשמט לא קשיא הא רבי הא רבנן. nishmat anishmat lo kashya
ha Rabbi ha Rabbanan. Now
רש''י Rashi has the exact opposite גירסא, girsa, okay? So רש''י's Rashi
גירסא girsa is,
let's start with the, let's go like this. נשמט אנשמט לא קשיא
הא באוהב הא בשונא. nishmat anishmat lo kashya ha b'ohev ha b'soneh.
So not נפסק אנפסק. nifsak anifsak. The נשמט nishmat case, if you're
a שונא, soneh, you're לא גולה, lo goleh, okay, because we'd say
it wasn't an accident. If you're an אוהב, ohev, you are גולה.
goleh. Okay, that's fine. Okay, so that explains that. So now here,
okay, so let's get this straight. So this would be a case
of שונא soneh and this is a case of אוהב. ohev. Okay,
so,
so we get here, right, this wasn't really an accident, if you're
a שונא soneh you're אינו גולה, eino goleh, if you're an אוהב
ohev it was an accident and you are גולה. goleh. Okay. So
how about this? Okay, נפסק אנפסק. nifsak anifsak. Why is that not,
what's the difference there? So he says הא רבי הא רבנן. ha
Rabbi ha Rabbanan. Who's the רבי Rabbi and the רבנן? Rabbanan? So
you remember, right, the רבי Rabbi and the רבנן, Rabbanan, right, is
the case about the guy with the hatchet, right, coming and, I
don't know why it's a hatchet, chopping the wood, right? So רבי
Rabbi says, right, so oh, I don't know, that's a pretty bad
picture. Anyway, רבי Rabbi says that the case is that he goes
into גלות golus is that he was holding onto it and that
the, the thing went off, right? So רבי Rabbi says it was
holding onto it and the רבנן Rabbanan say the top of it
flew off. Okay, so the top flew off. Right, so what the
גמרא Gemara is assuming here is is that not only is this
a question about, you know, whether it caused something else or was
it the thing I was doing itself? But it's, I mentioned this
when we did the רבי רבנן, Rebbi Rabanan, it's a general debate
about whether if like whether do I have like what's just physically
similar, that according to the רבנן, Rabanan, I am only
going to be חייב Chayav if I am holding part and part
separate. Okay, so therefore that's this case. So when we say you're
גולה, Goleh, this is the רבנן. Rabanan. Okay, because it's like you're
holding part and the top flew off. When you say you're אינו
גולה, Eino Goleh, that's רבי, Rebbi, because רבי Rebbi basically said, no,
you can't be sort of like left holding part of it. Okay,
like this case, you would be גולה Goleh because you're not left
holding any of it, you know, sort of like the splinter I
guess, you know, nobody holds any of the splinter, the splinter goes
by itself. Okay, but if you're left holding part of it, right,
רבי Rebbi would say you're אינו גולה. Eino Goleh. So when do
we say, so again, how does it work? שונא, Soneh, אינו גולה
Eino Goleh because we say it was on purpose. אוהב, Ohev, גולה
Goleh because we say it's the רבנן Rabanan that basically say that
it's that even if you're left holding part of it, when you're
left holding part of it, you're גולה. Goleh. In this version, the
אוהב Ohev is גולה Goleh because we say that it is it's
an accident. This case is an אינו גולה Eino Goleh because this
would be going
according to according to רבי Rebbi and רבי Rebbi says when you're
left holding part of it, you're not גולה. Goleh.
Right, so do you understand what this אמורא Amora is trying to
say? Okay, well, he has a teaching, he's not sure which תנא
Tanna to go by or which himself at the time, why would
he say according to two different Tannaitic opinions? He can give his
own opinion, right? Or why would he say רבי אומר? Rebbi Omer?
Yeah, so that's what the גמרא Gemara just says, that it's one
case where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is going according to the רבנן
Rabanan and one case where he's going according to רבי. Rebbi. I
don't know. I don't know what to say about that.
Okay, and I'm okay with the אוהב Ohev versus שונא, Soneh, they're
different cases.
Right, right, I understand.
All right, fine, but isn't this a new contradiction of the text
of the תורה Torah for רבי Rebbi saying that, doesn't it say
if the head of the axe flies off and kills somebody you
go into exile?
No, but רבי Rebbi said it doesn't mean the head of the
axe flies off, it means the axe causes the wood to chip
off and the splinter to fly off. השל הברזל מן העץ.
Hashel
habarzel min ha'etz.
So is the עץ?
Etz? That's what we learned. The way that they also say
רבי Rebbi rules that a woodchopper is not exiled if the head
of his axe flew off and killed someone. Correct.
Correct, only if the axe causes a chip of wood to fly
off of the wood being chopped.
And in the תורה Torah itself if the head flies?
That's not, that's they're debating how to read that case in the
תורה. Torah. Okay.
Okay. Okay, all right, so now we go on. Okay, fine. להיכן
גולין? Leichan Golin? Now, where where would they go to ערי מקלט?
Arei Miklat? ערי מקלט. Arei Miklat. להיכן גולין? Leichan Golin? Oh,
ערי מקלט. Arei Miklat. Fine. ושלש שבעבר הירדן ושלש
שבארץ כנען. U'shalosh shebe'ever hayarden v'shalosh shebe'eretz kena'an. There were three on
each side of the Jordan. שנאמר את שלש הערים תתנו מעבר הירדן
ואת שלש הערים תתנו בארץ כנען. Shene'emar es shalosh he'arim titnu me'ever
hayarden v'es shalosh he'arim titnu be'eretz kena'an. עד שלא נבחרו שלש שבארץ
ישראל לא היו שלש שבעבר הירדן
קולטות. Ad shelo nivcharu shalosh shebe'eretz yisrael lo hayu shalosh shebe'ever hayarden
koltot.
The three on the side on the Transjordan were not open for
business until they had designated until they had entered in and conquered
after 14 years and you know and then designated the three in
the land of Israel. שנאמר שש ערי מקלט תהיינה. Shene'emar sheish arei
miklat tihyena. There should be six. עד שיהיו ששתן קולטות כאחת. Ad
sheyiyu sheshtan koltot ke'achas.
Until all six are operating at once. ומכוונות להם דרכים מזו לזו.
U'mechuvnos lahem drachim mizo lizo.
And they would make like highways, you know, easy access roads from
one to the other. Now that's a little interesting because you would
think that you need easy access roads from the rest of the
all roads lead to Rome, all roads lead to the ערי מקלט,
Arei Miklat, right, you'd need clear access roads from other places in
the land to them, not necessarily from one to the next. Okay,
so I don't exactly get that but unless it means that if
you've got
I
like my cartoon in the whoops that has the exact right degree
of anyway, but if you've got right if you have like the
three here I guess I could draw my quick map of Israel,
okay like that, okay you got the three here right and this
is whatever the Jordan, okay you got your three here right and
they're going we're going to say that they're sort of parallel. So
if you've got your roads going like this, it sort of means
that if you're anywhere like in this region you can easily get
to them once you get to the main road. But it still
doesn't fully explain it, right, you know you would sort of you
would want roads leading whatever, so it's not exactly clear to me
why the focus is on the roads to one another. Okay, ומכוונות
להם דרכים מזו לזו. U'mechuvnos lahem drachim mizo lizo. שנאמר תכין לך
הדרך ושלשת. Shene'emar tachin lecha haderech v'shilashta. Fine. And you should divide
into thirds. ומוסרין להם שני תלמידי חכמים. U'mosrin lahem shnei talmidei chachamim.
Now this is, you know, of course this whole thing right about
the גואל הדם. Goel Hadam. It's to take something that had been
vigilante justice and to try to give and make the court control
it. And it still allows for that element of vigilante justice with
the גואל הדם, Goel Hadam, and we're going to see a debate
whether that's a רשות r'shus or a מצוה mitzvah or whatever, but
the more the court can control it, the better, right? So the
Torah just says he runs and then the court sends and brings
him to trial. But this actually has also the court, the תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim accompanying him on his way to the עיר מקלט.
ir miklat. Hope maybe it's like his armed guard or whatever. It
also, you know, for people that remember because it's similar in סוטה,
Sotah, right? It takes a case that the husband might have taken
his jealousy in his own hands and tries to, the court tries
to sort of control it. Although in the Torah, it's the husband
is taking it in his own hands but bringing her to the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, not just, not killing her, bringing her to
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. The גמרא Gemara brings בית דין Beis
Din into that equation. But if you remember in that case, when
it speaks about them going to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it
says the same thing, that the court has two תלמידי חכמים talmidei
chachamim accompanying him and so on. So we're sort of wondering why?
Because they don't sleep together?
Yeah, that's the explanation. I'm just saying the reality is here also
there's a function that they're doing. But the reality is that it
makes them part of the, gets them involved in the whole process.
Okay. ומוסרין לו שני תלמידי חכמים שמא יהרגנו בדרך וידברו אליו. Umosrin
lo shnei talmidei chachamim shema ye'hargenu baderech viy'dabru eilav. That the גואל
הדם Goel Hadam will come running up to them and try to
kill him. So these תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim will be able to
talk to the גואל הדם Goel Hadam and talk him out of
it. Now why תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim are the best people to
stop him from an attack of a גואל הדם, Goel Hadam, you
might, I personally would prefer like two big bodyguards, you know, with
some shoulder holsters or whatever. But anyway, they I guess they figure
that they'll represent rabbinic authority and therefore they'll have an effect at
convincing the guy out of it. רבי מאיר אומר הוא מדבר על
ידי עצמו. Rabbi Meir omer hu medaber al yedei atzmo. He doesn't
need the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim to, he can talk to the
guy himself and try to convince the גואל הדם Goel Hadam not
to kill him. שנאמר וזה דבר הרוצח. Shene'emar vezeh d'var harotzeach. This
is the דבר, davar, the דיבור, dibur, the words of the רוצח.
rotzeach. So what's he adding? Like of course and what and the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma doesn't think that he's allowed to try to
talk on his own? Is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir saying you don't
need תלמידי חכמים? talmidei chachamim?
Maybe the גואל הדם Goel Hadam doesn't want to hear from the
guy who...
Okay, who cares? Everybody's going to do what they can best do.
Like what's the, what are they actually debating?
Unless רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying that it's, maybe you're right,
maybe the rabbis are saying like don't let him talk because he's
just going to make things worse. Okay, that could be. Okay. רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר בתחילה אחד שוגג ואחד מזיד מקדימין לערי מקלט.
Rabbi Yose b'rabbi Yehuda omer batchila echad shogeg v'echad meizid makdimin l'arei
miklat.
Originally, like or at the outset, as soon as there's a death,
an, or whatever, a
homicide, you know, then the first thing they do is they send
everybody to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. Whether the assumption is that
it was a שוגג shogeg or מזיד meizid because you know, you
have to sort of control the situation. Right? מקלט. miklat. ובית דין
שולחין ומביאים אותו משם. U'veis din sholchin u'mevi'im oso misham. And then
בית דין Beis Din brings him from it. Like you go to
jail and then you sort of get brought to the court. מי
שנתחייב מיתה בבית דין הרגוהו. Mi shenischayev misa b'veis din haraguhu. Somebody
who's then found to have been done to, you know, it says
have done murder, he's executed. מי שלא נתחייב מיתה פטרוהו. Mi shelo
nischayev misa p'taruhu. And if somebody is basically found innocent completely, he'd
be completely freed. ומי שנתחייב גלות מחזירין אותו למקומו. U'mi shenischayev galus
machzirin oso limkomo. And somebody who actually did the act but it's
determined was in the
גלות galus category, you send him back to what his place was
because he was taken out from the ערי מקלט. arei miklat. שנאמר
והשיבו אותו העדה אל עיר מקלטו. Shene'emar v'heshivu oso ha'eidah el ir
miklato. Straight to the end.
בתחילה, batchila, this is what they used to do. But then you
just say oh, but now they...
No, no, no, no. בתחילה batchila doesn't mean they used to but
now it's different. But בתחילה batchila means at the, look at רש"י,
Rashi, first wide line at the bottom. תחילת דברים או תחילת משפט
כל הרוצחים
ואפילו מזידים. Techilas d'varim o techilas mishpat kol harotzchim v'afilu meizidim. Meaning
don't just say the שוגגים shogegim go to ערי מקלט. arei miklat.
The first thing we do is we send everybody to ערי מקלט.
arei miklat. We control the situation. Then guy says I'm innocent, I
don't have to go to ערי מקלט. arei miklat. Tough. Everybody goes
to ערי מקלט. arei miklat. And then we're going to process it.
Alright, so that's his point of בתחילה. batchila. Alright.
I thought that this is giving the מזידים meizidim too much of
a, you know, leeway to like blend in.
Whatever, I don't know. We're assuming that that's not a problem. תנו
רבנן. Tanu rabanan. שלש ערים הפריש משה בעבר הירדן וכנגדן הפריש יהושע
בארץ כנען. Shalosh arim hifrish Moshe b'ever hayarden u'chenegdan hifrish Yehoshua b'eretz
Kena'an. Three on one side, three on the other. משה Moshe and
יהושע. Yehoshua. ומכוונות היו כמין שתי שורות שבכרם. Umchuvanos hayu k'min shtei
shuros shebakarem.
And they were parallel, right? Like rows in a vineyard. Okay, you
know, you've got them all lined up nice, fine. Alright.
Now presumably that means not only this was parallel to this, it
probably means these were in a straight line, right? So I don't
know, okay, fine. חברון ביהודה כנגד בצר במדבר שכם בהר אפרים כנגד
רמות בגלעד קדש בנפתלי כנגד גולן בבשן.
Chevron b'Yehuda keneged Betzer
bamidbar Shechem b'har Ephraim keneged Ramous b'Gilad Kedesh b'Naftali keneged Golan b'Bashan.
Okay,
so those are the three places. I don't know how, does it
say there like which is the north?
It goes north, south, Reuben, Gad, you know, that whole thing. Right.
So if you just know which way they were.
Right. So okay, so what are they?
חברון Chevron is towards the north.
I know the top part.
No south. Right. כנגד בצר במדבר שכם. keneged Betzer bamidbar Shechem.
Who knows that type people's knowledge of Israel? Is שכם *Shechem* lower
than חברון Hevron *Hevron*?
People who know where שכם *Shechem* is?
That would be a nice place to have a map.
I wish I had a map. Fabulous. Here, he has it right
here. Where's שכם *Shechem* and חברון Hevron
*Hevron*?
Oh,
it's the opposite.
Oh fine, that just shows my knowledge of Israeli geography. חברון Hevron,
*Hevron*, שכם *Shechem*, and קדש Kadesh *Kadesh*.
Okay fine, we're going the other way then.
The thing is the way he draws it, it's like... look here,
like almost like steps. Like one's a little bit lower than...
this actually makes sense. It doesn't fit into the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
but it makes sense. You want to distribute it like that. Okay,
anyway.
Fine.
All right, let's go on. Okay. All right, so okay. ושלשת *Ushilashta*,
you shall third it, ומשולשים *umeshulashim*, that it should be... that they
should be equally thirded. Now what does that mean? שהן מדרום לחברון
כחברון לשכם ומחברון לשכם כשכם לקדש ומשכם לקדש כקדש לצפון בעבר הירדן
*shehein midarom leHevron keHevron leShechem u-meHevron leShechem keShechem leKadesh u-meShechem leKadesh keKadesh
la-Tzafon be-ever ha-Yarden*. Okay fine. So basically it means that this distance
from בצר *Betzer* to the bottom... or what were we doing? בצר
*Betzer*? We're doing... which side are we doing? No, we're doing חברון
*Hevron*, right? We're doing this side. ושלשת *Ushilashta*...
right, this distance, okay, X, is equal to this distance, is equal
to this distance, is equal to this distance. Okay? So the land
is divided into fourths but it's... you know, it's funny that that's
the word thirds, but okay, you know. There's three...
there are three of them.
But each distance is the same. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*...
okay. Okay. תלת *Tlat*... okay wait... בעבר הירדן תלת בארץ ישראל תלת
*Be-ever ha-Yarden tlat be-Eretz Yisrael tlat*. Three on one side, three on
the other. אמר אביי Amar Abaye. *Amar Abaye*: בגלעד *be-Gilad*... I'm sorry...
did I skip... No, בעבר הירדן תלת בארץ ישראל תלת *be-ever ha-Yarden
tlat be-Eretz Yisrael tlat*? What? On one side of the Jordan there's
three, there's only two and a half tribes. On the other side
there's three, it's much more populous. You should need many more in
the land of Israel than on the other side of Israel. אמר
אביי Abaye *Amar Abaye*: בגלעד שכיחי רוצחים *be-Gilad shechichi rotzchim*.
You know, in the גלעד *Gilad* area there's a lot of murderers
on that side of the Jordan. So you need more... so therefore
here you need more ערי מקלט arei miklat, *Arei
Miklat*. דכתיב *De-chtiv*, because the verse says, גלעד קרית פועלי און *Gilad
kiryat poalei aven*, גלעד *Gilad* is a city of those who do
evil, עקובה מדם *akuva mi-dam*, it is the footsteps of blood. מאי
עקובה מדם *Mai akuva mi-dam*? אמר רבי Rebbe אלעזר *Amar Rabbi Elazar*
שהיו עוקבים להרוג נפשות *shehayu oklavim laharog nefashot*, that they would like
run out, like they would they would plot to kill people. It
wasn't just as a moment of passion. So that side of the
Jordan there were more murderers. ומאי שנא מהאי גיסא ומהאי גיסא דמרחקי
ומאי שנא מציעי דמקרבי *U-mai shna me-hai gisa u-me-hai gisa de-marchaki u-mai
shna metzi-ei de-mekarvi*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has a problem. This
all looks very equally divided. But if you think about where you
are in the land, okay, if you're in the top... in the...
this area or this area, then your average distance you're going to
have to travel will be a half X, right, and sometimes you'll
have to travel a full X if you're way up
here, right? Whereas here,
if you're here, the most you would ever have to travel is
half X, right? And the average distance you'd actually travel is a
quarter X. Do you see that? Right? If you're in this place
of the land, the longest you would have to travel to get
to an עיר מקלט ir miklat, *Ir Miklat* would be X if
you were here. The average... sometimes it'd be three-quarters, sometimes it'd be
a half. Here, the most you'd have to travel is a half
X, and the average you'd have to travel is a quarter X.
Okay, so why is that? Like why is it easier... so the
obvious answer is that the more population is more in the center
of the land than at the edges of the land. But let's
see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* answers. Okay. ומאי שנא מהאי גיסא
ומהאי גיסא דמרחקי *U-mai shna me-hai gisa u-me-hai gisa de-marchaki* at the
north and at the south it's a greater distance ומאי שנא מציעי
דמקרבי *u-mai shna metzi-ei de-mekarvi* in the middle it's a shorter distance.
אמר אביי *Amar Abaye*: בשכם נמי שכיחי רוצחים *be-Shechem nami shechichi rotzchim*.
Yeah, because in שכם *Shechem*, here, in these middle... in right right
in the middle of the land, there's a lot of murderers. So
rather than it being more populous, it's actually just more dense in
murderers. Okay. דכתיב *De-chtiv*, וכחכי איש גדודים חבר כהנים kohanim דרך ירצחו
שכמה *u-ke-chakei ish gedudim chaver kohanim derech yeratzchu Shechema*. And you know,
when they... how do they translate this verse here?
You're not up to there? Okay.
Hold on.
And as... and as troops of robbers wait for a man, so
does the band of priests, they murder in the way towards שכם
*Shechem*.
So troops... so troops like וכחכי *ke-chakei* like לחכות *le-chakot*. As troops
of robbers wait for a man, so the כהנים *Kohanim* will murder
on the way on the way going to שכם *Shechem*. So you
see שכם *Shechem* is associated with murder. מאי חבר כהנים *Mai chaver
kohanim* what does it mean What, priests all of a sudden are
the ones that are murdering? Why does it mention priests?
אמר רבי Rebbe אלעזר שהיו מתחברים להרוג נפשות ככהנים הללו. shehayu mitchabrim
laharog nefashot kekohanim halalu. So מתחברים mitchabrim לחלוק תרומה בבית הגרנות. lachlok
terumah be-veit ha-geranot. The same way כהנים band together to go and
collect grain in the threshing floors, you know, for their תרומה, terumah,
so people would band together to commit murder. This explanation still doesn't
exactly explain it. ותו ליכא? Ve-tu lika? Now one minute. Is there
only six? והכתיב Ve-haktive עליהם תתנו ארבעים ושתיים עיר? aleichem titnu arbaim
u-shtayim ir? That they would add 42 ערי מקלט, arei miklat? right?
I mean that's just the פשט pshat of the פסוקים. pesukim. What's
the difference between the primary six and the additional 42? אמר אביי.
הללו קולטות בין לדעת בין שלא לדעת, הללו לדעת קולטות שלא לדעת
אינו קולטות. halalu koltot bein le-daat bein she-lo le-daat, halalu le-daat koltot
she-lo le-daat eino koltot. The six correct sort of
are absorbed, right, whether intentionally or unintentionally. רש״י Rashi says it means
whether you went there for the sake of
sanctuary or whether you just happened to be there. Whereas the other
42 will only protect you, legally protect you, I mean nobody can
protect you unless you have an invisible unless you have a shield,
you know. But anyway, but the other 42 will only legally protect
you if you went there specifically for the sake of sanctuary. Okay,
so וחברון עיר מקלט היא? ve-Hevron ir miklat hi? Now the גמרא
says one minute, is חברון really one of the ערי מקלט? arei
miklat,
והכתיב, Ve-haktive, doesn't it say ויתנו לכלב את חברון כאשר דבר משה?
vayitnu le-Kaleiv et Hevron kaasher diber Moshe? They gave כלב את חברון,
Kaleiv et Hevron, they gave כלב Kaleiv חברון as משה Moshe had
said to him. ואמר אביי. Ve-amar Abaye. פרברה. Parvara. דכתיב את שדה
העיר ואת חצריה נתנו לכלב בן יפונה. de-chtive et sedeih ha-ir ve-et
hatzereiha natnu le-Kaleiv ben Yefuneh.
So wait, what's the question, that they gave it to כלב? Kaleiv?
I guess they would assume that they wouldn't give it to כלב
Kaleiv if it was a public city.
Okay, so
presumably they're just saying it was a public city, an עיר מקלט,
ir miklat? you wouldn't give it to a personal ownership. So אביי
says fine, they gave a suburb to כלב, Kaleiv, they didn't actually
give him the city itself.
Okay, so where were we? דכתיב את שדה העיר ואת חצריה נתנו
לכלב בן יפונה. de-chtive et sedeih ha-ir ve-et hatzereiha natnu le-Kaleiv ben
Yefuneh. They only gave him the fields outside, they didn't give him
the city itself. וקדש עיר מקלט הוי? Ve-Kadesh ir miklat havei? Was
קדש Kadesh really an עיר מקלט? ir miklat? והכתיב, Ve-haktive, doesn't it
say וערי מבצר הצדיקים, ve-arei mivtzar ha-tzadikim,
צרים וחמת ורקת וכנרת? Tzirim ve-Hamat ve-Rakat ve-Chinneret? So these are the
fortified cities. וקדש ואדרי ועין חצור. ve-Kadesh ve-Edrei ve-Ein Hatzor. So קדש
Kadesh was a fortified city. So how does that prove that it
wasn't an עיר מקלט? ir miklat דתניא, De-tanya, because we learn in
a ברייתא, Baraita, I mean it would be good for an עיר
מקלט ir miklat to be a fortified city, but because we learn
in the ברייתא, Baraita, ערי מקלט הללו אין עושים אותם לא עיירות
קטנות ולא כרכים גדולים. arei miklat halalu ein osim otam lo ayarot
ketanot ve-lo kerachim gedolim. You don't make these ערי מקלט, arei miklat.
you don't make them little villages and you don't make them big
cities. אלא עיירות בינוניות. Ela ayarot beinoniyot. You make them like middle-sized
towns. Okay, we'll see why in a minute. So anyway, but clearly,
if you don't make it a big city, so if it's an
עיר מבצר, ir mivtzar, that is, like a fortified city is a
big city. So קדש Kadesh. can't be an עיר מקלט ir miklat,
if it's this big fortified city. אמר רב יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef.
תרתי קדש הוו. Tartei Kadesh havu. There are two places called קדש.
Kadesh, Fine. אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi. כדאמרן סליקום ואקרא דסליקום.
Ke-demaran Selikum ve-akra de-Selikum. Like there's this place, one place is called
סליקום Selikum and another place is called the this seems to be
a different answer, not that there's two places called קדש, Kadesh but
similar to the כלב Kaleiv answer before about חברון, there's you know,
there's the main city of קדש Kadesh which is the fortified city,
that's not an עיר מקלט, ir miklat. and then there's the village
of קדש Kadesh or the town of קדש Kadesh which is nearby,
and that is the עיר מקלט. ir miklat, Okay, so you have
two it's not that there are literally two separate cities. There's קדש
Kadesh and there's קדש Kadesh suburbs. So קדש Kadesh the main city
is not עיר מקלט, ir miklat. קדש suburbs is an עיר מקלט.
Ir Miklat.
גופא. Gufa. Now let's go back and look at that statement that
we just said. ערי מקלט הללו אין עושים אותם לא עיירות קטנות
ולא כרכים גדולים. arei miklat halalu ein osim otam lo ayarot ketanot
ve-lo kerachim gedolim. You don't make them little villages and you don't
make them big cities. אלא עיירות בינוניות. Ela ayarot beinoniyot. But middle-sized
towns. ומושיבים אותם אלא במקום מים. Ve-moshivim otam ela bi-mkom mayim. And
you have to make sure that they are, you know,
that they have like the bare necessities of life. You only settle
them in a place where there's water. ואם אין שם מים מביאים
להם מים. Ve-im ein sham mayim mevi-im lahem mayim. If there's not
natural water there,
you bring water there, you ship water there. ואין מושיבים אותם אלא
במקום שווקים. Ve-ein moshivim otam ela bi-mkom shevakim. And you put them
in places where there are markets. Because, you know, people need to
get their food. ואין מושיבים אותם אלא במקום אוכלוסין. Ve-ein moshivim otam
ela bi-mkom ochlusin. And you only put them in a place where
there's like a population, not where it's I mean, which would seem
to be related to the idea of a middle-sized town. But maybe
it means that they're not like in the middle of nowhere, you
know, that there are people that are in the surrounding towns or
something.
נתמעטו אוכלוסיהם. Nitmaatu ochluseihem. Now let's say the population went down, so,
you know, I don't know, people left it or other things. מוסיפים
עליהם. Mosifim aleihem. Then you would add. Now of course, who's going
to agree to add? What, do you mean you would add? You
force people to move there? Like I don't get that exactly. Okay,
you provide incentives maybe, I'm not sure.
נתמעטו דיוריהם. Nitmaatu diyureihem. Okay. מביאים להם כהנים לויים וישראלים. Mevi-im lahem
kohanim Leviyim ve-Yisraelim. I'm not exactly sure about the difference of אוכלוסיהם
ochluseihem and דיוריהם. diyureihem. It seems like אוכלוסיהם ochluseihem might mean the
population that surrounds the place and וצמתו דיוריהון vitzmatu diyureihon and the
actual inhabitants themselves have shrunk. So then you bring in new inhabitants.
Again, I don't know how you do these transfer populations, but anyway,
and you bring in, you make sure that it's a nice diversity,
כהן לוי ישראל. Kohen Levi Yisrael. ואין מוכרין להם
לא כלי זיין ולא כלי מצודה, ve'ein mochrin lahem lo klei zayin
velo klei metzudah, you don't sell there weapons. Yeah, that's the best
thing to be selling in an עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat. The reason
you wouldn't sell it, maybe the guy says I want it for
self-defense, but you don't want the גואל הדם Goel HaDam to come
there and to find a weapon available for him to kill this
guy. Okay, so you don't sell, I mean, you really do wonder
who wants to live in an עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat Like, you
know, if you have, I mean, would they be afraid that, you
know, there could be גואלי הדם Goalei HaDam that are entering in
at random hours? Anyway, but maybe I don't know, maybe they were
protected and people, people
respected those, you know, those rules. Anyway fine. You don't sell, you
don't sell murder weapon, you don't sell weapons, ולא כלי מצודה, velo
klei metzudah, even trapping weapons, you know, because, you know, you have
a bear trap or whatever you can also use it on a
person. דברי רבי נחמיה, Divrei Rabbi Nechemia, that's what Rabbi Nechemia says.
וחכמים מתירין. veChachamim matirin. Interestingly, the חכמים Chachamim allow it. ושוין, veShavin,
but they agree שאין פורסין בתוכן מצודות, she'ein porsin betochan metzudot, you
don't spread out nets there again for trapping purposes. ואין מפשילין לתוכן
חבלים ve'ein mapshilin letochan chavalim and you don't also like, you know,
dry, you know, sort of dry out or whatever, you know, do
these, make ropes there for similar reasons that it could be used
by the, by the גואל הדם. Goel HaDam. Why that's different than
the traps, I don't know. That pretty much sounds like traps to
me. But okay.
Hold on, let me just check רש"י Rashi for a minute.
Right, so רש"י Rashi says, just to go back to the previous
point, that אוכלוסין uchlusin is what I said, it's the population surrounding
it, not the population there itself.
And the reason you want a big population in the neighborhood is
not just that they should be able to have provisions that they
need, but also if they're isolated, they're open for attack. So therefore
you want a lot of place, you know, you want towns in
the, in the neighborhood so the less isolated they are, the less
open they are for attack.
And let me just see this רש"י Rashi about, okay, so רש"י
Rashi does not explain the difference here between why the Rabbis could
be, could be okay with selling traps and weapons but not okay
with selling nets. Maybe the גמרא will explain it.
Let's take a look.
Okay, ואין מפשילין לתוכן חבלים כדי שלא תהא רגל גואל הדם מצויה.
ve'ein mapshilin letochan chavalim kedei shelo tehei regel Goel HaDam metzuyah. You
don't have these things available so as not to encourage the גואל
הדם Goel HaDam to come to the town thinking that they will
be able to find the weapons that they need to, to kill
this person.
Okay. אמר רבי יצחק מאי קרא? Amar Rabbi Yitzchak mai kra? What's
the verse that, that you make sure that in the, that in
this עיר מקלט Ir Miklat? they have the necessities of life? You
know, they have water and they have all these other things. שנאמר
ונס אל אחת הערים האל וחי, shenemar venas el achat he'arim ha'eleh
vachai, he should run to one of these cities and live. עביד
ליה מידי דתהוי ליה חיותא, avid lei midei d'tehavi lei chiyuta, you
have to make sure that once he gets there he's able to
have the, he's able to live, he has the necessities of life.
Okay. תנא ותנא ברייתא, Tana vetana baraita, תלמיד
שגלה מגלין רבו עמו. talmid shegalah maglin rabbo imo. So we don't
unpack that ברייתא baraita about the ropes versus the weapons. I really
don't have any good explanation about that.
Okay. תנא ותנא ברייתא, Tana vetana baraita, תלמיד שגלה מגלין רבו עמו.
talmid shegalah maglin rabbo imo. If a student is exiled, his רבי
Rebbe. goes with him, which is, I always found this so bizarre.
You're going to force this רבי Rebbe, to uproot from his location
because his student accidentally killed somebody? And what about all the other
students that he's leaving behind? You know, now everybody has to go
to this עיר מקלט? ir miklat, Like, I never really understood this.
Okay, anyway, שנאמר וחי, shenemar vachai,
to live, and of course life means spiritual life. So you have
to go with your רבי. Rebbe If you need water, you need
תורה. Torah. All
right. עביד ליה מידי דתהוי ליה חיותא, avid lei midei d'tehavi lei
chiyuta, bring him something that will be life, and here life means
spiritual life. אמר רבי זירא מכאן שלא ישנה אדם לתלמיד שאינו הגון.
Amar Rabbi Zeira mikan shelo yeshaneh adam letalmid she'eino hagun. This teaches
you to be very careful not to teach somebody who doesn't deserve
to be there because assuming that people, now this is an interesting
assumption, that somebody who's going to accidentally kill somebody, it's only because,
you know, either, either somehow this, you know, God made this happen
because you were, because this person was, you know, you know, was
somehow, you know, you know, this doesn't happen to righteous people. God
makes sure that these accidents only happen to righteous people type of
a thing. Or no, that again it happened because of a certain
degree of negligence and people that are taking the right approach to
the sanctity and, you know, of human life are going to be
hyper-vigilant and it won't happen. So it's a lesson to you as
a רבי, Rebbe don't teach somebody who is, you know, who's not
of ideal character because somebody who's not of ideal character could do,
could have these accidents and then you'll wind up going into exile.
Okay, yes, well you had something there about the difference between ropes
and weapons, what does it say?
Yeah, it
says מסכת מכות Masechet Makkot because it has many people, and the
גואל הדם goel hadam may enter the boundaries, and then in these
cases it talks also for an
indiscriminate space sometimes. So the problem is that you might slip in.
Not that it's a murderer, but it might slip in.
Okay. All right, so now the גמרא says like this.
Okay. Moving on. אמר יוחנן: Amar Yochanan: הרב שגלה מגלין ישיבתו עמו.
Harav shegala maglin yeshivato imo.
Okay,
now it's the flip. If the רבי Rebbe actually
killed somebody and he goes into גלות, galut, the whole ישיבה yeshiva
goes with him because, you know, if the student needs the רבי
Rebbe for his spiritual life, the רבי needs the students.
איני? eini? Is this really true?
ואמר רבי יוחנן: ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan: מנין לדברי תורה שהן קולטין? minayin
l'divrei Torah shehen koltin? How do you know that the words of
תורה Torah actually provide sanctuary? Which presumably means that if somebody is
a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham or is a teacher of תורה Torah
or whatever, I mean, I don't know if you'd have to actively
be teaching, anyway the laws that restrict the גואל הדם goel hadam
would apply to this person's like going around with an invisible force
field, you know? שנאמר shene'emar because it says את בצר במדבר et
Betzer bamidbar וכתיב בתריה vechtiv batreih וזאת התורה. vezot haTorah. Okay, so
it juxtaposes the words וזאת התורה vezot haTorah to the ערי מקלט.
arei miklat, So the תורה Torah itself serves as an עיר מקלט,
ir miklat. so you don't have to go anywhere. ולא קשיא: Velo
kashya: הא בעידנא דעסיק בה הא בעידנא דלא עסיק בה. ha b'idna
d'asik bah ha b'idna d'lo asik bah. Fine. When you're actively learning
תורה, Torah, you know, you have this invisible force field around you
and the גואל הדם, goel hadam, if he knows the הלכה, halacha,
knows it's hands off. But as soon as you stop learning תורה,
Torah, then, you know, you're free. So, so now, fine. So bottom
line is even a רבי who killed somebody would have to go
to an עיר מקלט. ir miklat Now would you have to? Would
it be like, hey, if you want to stay outside the עיר
מקלט ir miklat and hope you won't, you know? Because it's not
just the purpose of עיר מקלט ir miklat. is not just to
protect. There's, it's a punishment and a כפרה kapara and a protection,
right? So even if תורה Torah protects, that's the funny thing. Like,
fine, תורה Torah protects, but he's not being, where's his punishment and
where's his כפרה, kapara, right? He needs to go into exile for
that purpose. So it's interesting that the גמרא is just focusing on
the protection aspect. Okay.
It's like the story of David where as long as he's studying...
Yeah, sort of like the story of David and the מלאך המות.
Malach Hamavet. Exactly.
ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, okay, and if you want, I could say:
מאי קולטין? Mai koltin? ממלאך המות. Mimalach hamavet. Now see, there you
go, exactly as you were saying. No, קולטין koltin does not mean
that it protects you from the גואל הדם. goel hadam. קולטין koltin
means that it protects you from the angel of death. The גואל
הדם goel hadam can kill you if you're not in the עיר
מקלט. ir miklat Okay, כי הא דרב חסדא, ki ha d'Rav Chisda,
like רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, here he goes, דוד David exactly like
you said, הוה יתיב וגריס בי רב. hava yativ vegaris bei rav.
He was sitting and learning in the house of רב. Rav. וחזא
דלא יכיל שליחא דמלאכא דמותא למיקרב לגביה, vechaza d'la yachil shelicha d'malacha
d'muta l'mikrav legabeih, and the, and the angel of the מלאך המות
Malach Hamavet was not able to get close to him because his
תורה Torah was protecting him, דלא הוה פסק פומיה מגירסא, d'la hava
pasik pumieh migirsa, because he never would stop, the words of תורה
Torah never leave his lips. So סליק, salik, so what did the
מלאך המות Malach Hamavet do? Or the מלאך המות Malach Hamavet emissary?
ויתיב ארזא דבי רב. veyativ arza d'bei rav. He went and he
sat on the cedar tree. פקע ארזא, paka arza, so the cedar
tree split in half because the מלאך המות Malach Hamavet was there.
ושתיק, veshatik, and he like looked up, astounded for a second, and
he was silent and תורה Torah wasn't on his lips. ויכיל ליה,
veyachil leih, and then he was able to attack it. Okay, but
still, so that's like a similar story by דוד, David, המלך דוד.
Hamelech David. But still, it's fascinating because it assumes that if the
תורה Torah would provide sanctuary, you wouldn't have to go, you know?
But why not? Like if the guy killed somebody, he needs, the
exile was part of the punishment. It's not just about the sanctuary.
Okay, אמר רבי תנחום בר חנילאי: Amar Rabbi Tanchum bar Chanilai: מפני
מה זכה ראובן לימנות בהצלה תחילה? Mipnei mah zachah Reuven limanot b'hatzalah
techilah? Why was ראובן Reuven first mentioned in the salvation, meaning in
the cities of the ערי מקלט, it first mentions those that were
in the land of ראובן? Reuven? Okay, so it says,
let me just check רש"י. Rashi.
Yeah. Okay, right. Exactly. So why was his, why was the area
of ראובן Reuven mentioned where the עיר מקלט is first?
So, where were we?
תחילה, techilah, שנאמר, shene'emar, מפני שהוא פתח בהצלה תחילה, mipnei shehu patach
b'hatzalah techilah, because he was the first one that tried to save
somebody from being killed. שנאמר וישמע ראובן ויצילהו מידם. Shene'emar Vayishma Reuven
Vayatzileihu Miyadam. So he wasn't successful, but at least he was the
one that tried to stand up for יוסף Yosef and to try
to save him from being killed. דרש רבי שמלאי: Darash Rabbi Simlai:
מאי דכתיב? mai d'chtiv? What's meant by the verse: אז יבדיל משה
שלש ערים בעבר הירדן מזרח שמש? Az yavdil Moshe shalosh arim b'ever
haYarden mizrach shamesh? He separated three cities. אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא
למשה: Amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Moshe:
מזרח שמש לרוצחין. Mizrach shamesh lerotzchin. So מזרח שמש, mizrach shamesh, let
the sun shine forth for the murderers. Meaning, make sure that they
have all the provisions that they need. It's funny, it's calling them
murderers, רוצחין, rotzchin, right? Not הורגים horgim or whatever. רוצח, rotzeach, אה,
וזה דבר הרוצח, vezeh devar harotzeach, right?
So I mean, in our language, a murderer is a language we
use for intentional, right? As opposed to manslaughter or killing somebody, but
anyway, so it's a pretty heavy word. Anyway, so God says: We
make sure that even if they're running to the עיר מקלט *Ir
Miklat*, the sun is shining for them, that they still have what
they need. איכא דאמרי אמרי ליה *Ika damri amrei lei*, הזרחת שמש
לרוצחים *hazrachat shemesh lerotzhim*, it was like a בתמיה *bitmiya*. What? Oh
no, excuse me, not בתמיה *bitmiya*, excuse me. הזרחת שמש לרוצחים *hazrachat
shemesh lerotzhim*. Yes, she did a good job. You separated the cities
and you've done what you needed to do in terms of making
the sun shine, meaning making sure that they're protected. דרש סימאי *Darsh
Simai*, מאי דכתיב *mai dichtiv*, what's meant by the verse, אוהב כסף
לא ישבע כסף *ohev kesef lo yisba kesef*, one who loves money
will not be satisfied with money, ומי אוהב בהמון לא תבואה *u'mi
ohev be'hamon lo tevuah*, and the one who
loves with
the masses will not have grain. What does this mean? אוהב כסף
לא ישבע כסף *ohev kesef lo yisba kesef*, זה משה רבינו *zeh
Moshe Rabbeinu*, שהיה יודע שאין שלוש ערים שבעבר הירדן קolטות עד שלא
נבחרו שלוש שבארץ כנען *shehayah yodea she’ein shalosh arim shebe’ever hayarden koltot
ad shelo nivcharu shalosh shebe’eretz kena’an*. כסף *kesef* is being understood not
as money but as מצוות mitzvos. *mitzvos*. משה *Moshe* knew, he loves
מצוות *mitzvos*. And he knew that the three he would set in
עבר הירדן *ever hayarden* would not go into operation until the three
in ארץ כנען *eretz kena'an*. You could have said, let somebody else
do it, it's not even going to go into operation yet, why
should I bother? ואמר *ve'amar*, nevertheless, מצוה שבאה לידי אקיימנה *mitzvah sheba'ah
leyadi akaymena*. A מצוה *mitzvah* that I have an opportunity to do
I'll do it even if it won't yet be effective in my
lifetime. That's אוהב כסף *ohev kesef*, somebody who so loves מצוות *mitzvos*
he's never enough, he always has to find more opportunities for doing
מצוות *mitzvos*. ומי אוהב בהמון לא תבואה *u'mi ohev be'hamon lo tevuah*.
Now what does that mean? The one who loves with the masses
will not have grain. למי נאה ללמד lelamed. בהמון *lemi na'eh lelamed
be'hamon*, who is the one who is appropriate to teach in masses,
to be דורש תורה Torah, ברבים *doresh Torah berabbim*, מי שכל תבואה
שלו *mi shekol tevuah shelo*, the one who has all the grain.
Grain is a
classic metaphor for תורה Torah *Torah* knowledge. Reading לו תבואה *lo tevuah*
as with a ו *vav*, not with an א *alef*. He is
the one that somebody who has all תורה Torah. *Torah* knowledge, that's
the one who can give דרשות drashos. *drashos* to the masses. והיינו
דאמר רבי אלעזר מאי דכתיב *ve'hainu d'amar Rabbi Elazar mai dichtiv*, what's
meant by the verse, מי ימלל גבורות ה' ישמיע כל תהלתו *mi
yemallel gevurot Hashem yashmia kol tehillato*, who will speak the mighty deeds
of God and let known all of God's glory? למי נאה למלל
גבורות ה' *lemi na'eh le'mallel gevurot Hashem*, to whom is it most
fitting to speak of the glories of God? למי שיכול להשמיע כל
תהלתו *lemi sheyachol le'hashmia kol tehillato*. Somebody who really has mastery on
all the fields of תורה Torah *Torah* and can really give full
glory to God because of all of his knowledge. ותנא רבנן ותימא
רבה בר מרי אמרי *v'tana rabbanan v'teima Rabbah bar Mari amrei*, מי
אוהב בהמון לו תבואה *mi ohev be'hamon lo tevuah*. Who the one
who loves in the masses, he has grain, now they've actually switched
the א *alef* to the ו *vav* because that's how we're reading
it, not doesn't have grain, but has grain. כל האוהב ללמד בהמון
*kol haohev
lelamed be'hamon*, anybody who loves teaching in the masses, בהמון לו תבואה
*be'hamon lo tevuah*, יהבו ליה *yehavu lei*, will have grain. Let me
just check
רש"י
*Rashi* here. Oh no, they take out the word ללמד *lelamed*. כל
האוהב *kol haohev*, somebody who shows great love towards people, it's a
very different point, בהמון *be'hamon*, and is beloved in the masses, somebody
who's a beloved person, לו תבואה *lo tevuah*, that person will merit
having תורה Torah *Torah*. It's not who gets to teach in the
masses if you already know תורה Torah *Torah*, somebody who is very
beloved, that person will get תורה Torah *Torah*. רש"י *Rashi* says, התורה
מחזרת עליו ועל זרעו *haTorah mechazeret alav v'al zaro*. It says, מי
אוהב בהמון האוהב תלמיד חכם התורה מחזרת עליו ועל זרעו *mi ohev
be'hamon ha'ohev talmid chacham haTorah mechazeret alav v'al zaro*. האי מאן דרחים
רבנן הוו ליה בנין רבנן *hai man derachim rabbanan havu lei banin
rabbanan*. Not just that you are loved and beloved, but it means
that you love תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim*. Let's try it one last
time. כל האוהב בהמון *kol haohev be'hamon*, anybody who loves those who
teach תורה Torah, *Torah* or תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim*, לו תבואה *lo
tevuah* will himself get תורה Torah *Torah*. שדי בהו רבנן עינייהו ברבא
בריה דרב *shadi behu rabbanan einaihu be'Rabba berei de'Rav*. And then the
Rabbis turned their eyes and looked at רבא בריה דרב *Rabba berei
de'Rav* because he was somebody who greatly
loved תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim* and he merited that his children were
תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim*. רש"י אומר *Rashi omer*, כל האוהב ללמד בהמון
לו תבואה *kol haohev lelamed be'hamon lo tevuah*. Like we said before,
if you love teach, but before we said who has the right
to teach to the masses, somebody who has תורה Torah *Torah*, and
here we're reversing the order. Anybody who loves to learn in a
masses will get תורה Torah *Torah*. והיינו דאמר רבי יהושע בן חנינא
מאי דכתיב *ve'hainu d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chanina mai dichtiv*, חרב אל
הבדים ונואלו *cherev el habadim veno'alu*, a sword on the בדים *badim*
and they will grow weary. What does that mean? חרב על צואריהם
של שונאיהם של תלמידי חכמים *cherev al tzavareihem shel soneihem shel talmidei
chachamim*, a sword should be against the necks of the haters of
תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim*, which means the תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim* שיושבים
ועוסקים בתורה בד בבד *sheyoshvim v'oskim baTorah bad bevad*, they go learn
תורה Torah *Torah* alone, you're learning תורה *Torah* you're sitting in a
library. Everybody's learning alone. Everybody's quiet. This is the גמרא *Gemara* about
learning בחברותא *bechavruta*. Okay,
so, so ולא עוד אלא שמתפשין. And so besides the fact that
maybe you know you don't have the energy and the religious experience
of learning and the connection to somebody else, it actually is counterproductive
to your learning. You'll grow stupid if you learn alone. כתיב הכא
ונואלו, ksiv hacha venoalu, you grow weary, וכתיב התם אשר נואלנו, uchsiv
hasam asher noalnu, that we have become been foolish. ולא עוד אלא
שחוטאין, velo od ela shechot'in, it's a sin. Okay, it's not just
maybe I don't learn as much. No, you're actually sinning, שנאמר ואשר
חטאנו אשר נואלנו ואשר חטאנו. shene'emar va'asher chatanu asher noalnu va'asher chatanu.
Okay, ואיבעית אימא מהכא, ve'iba'is eima mehacha, נואלו שרי צוען, noalu sarei
tzo'an, where it's foolish the officers of or the leaders of צוען.
Tzo'an. So this way is reading it, כל האוהב ללמוד בהמון kol
ha'ohev lilmod bahamon as opposed to who gets to teach the masses?
Somebody who has תורה, it's the opposite. Anybody who loves learning, not
teaching, learning with masses of people in a big בית מדרש beis
medrash with a lot of קול תורה, kol torah, that person will
get will get תורה knowledge. Okay. רבינא Ravina אמר כל האוהב ללמד
בהמון לא תועה. amar kol ha'ohev lelamed bahamon lo to'eh. So not
ללמוד lilmod but ללמד. So this is to teach. Anybody who loves
to teach in the masses will get תורה. והיינו דאמר רבי
הרבה תורה למדתי מרבותי, vehainu de'amar rebbi harbeh torah lamadeti merabotai, much
תורה I learned from my Rebbes, ומחברי יותר מהם, umechaveirai yoser mehem,
from my colleagues more than them, ומתלמידי יותר מכולם, umisalmidei yoser mikulam,
but the most I learned from my students. So this is, so
it's three דרשות. One is, who has the right to teach people
if you already have תורה knowledge. Number one. Number two is, if
you love learning with a lot of people, you'll get תורה knowledge.
And number three is, if you love teaching a lot of people,
you'll get תורה knowledge. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי מאי דכתיב, amar
rebbi yehoshua ben levi mai dechsiv, what's meant by the verse, עומדות
היו רגלינו בשעריך ירושלים, omdos hayu ragleinu bish'arayich yerushalayim, our legs were
standing in your gates Jerusalem.
מי גרם לרגלינו שיעמדו במלחמה, mi garam leragleinu she'ya'amdu bamilchama,
who allowed our legs to stand in war, meaning like the war
of תורה, us to have this power in
תורה knowledge, okay, שערי ירושלים, sha'arei yerushalayim, the gates of Jerusalem, שהיו
עוסקין בתורה, shehayu oskin batorah, that we were learning תורה and like
a sense of a gate, a city gate is where all the
business happens, where all the masses gather, that's where the markets are,
so it's because of that תורה learning with a group, you know,
with a group of people, that's why we were able. Okay.
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי מאי דכתיב, amar rebbi yehoshua ben levi
mai dechsiv, what's meant by the verse, שיר המעלות לדוד שמחתי באומרים
לי בית ה' נלך, shir hama'alos ledavid samachti be'omrim li beis hashem
neilech, I rejoiced when they said to me, let us go to
the house of God. אמר דוד David לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, lifnei
hakadosh baruch hu, ריבונו של עולם, ribono shel olam, שמעתי בני אדם
שהיו אומרים מתי ימות זקן זה ויבא שלמה בנו ויבנה בית הבחירה,
shamati benei adam shehayu omrim masai yamut zaken zeh veyavo shelomo beno
veyivneh beis habechirah, I heard that people were saying to me, when
is this old guy going to finally die and his son שלמה
Shlomo will take over and then we'll build be able to build
the Temple. ונעלה לרגל, vena'aleh leregel,
and we'll be
עולה לרגל. oleh leregel. ושמחתי, vesamachti, and I rejoiced. Rather than thinking
like everybody wants me to die, I said, oh, everybody wants to
get closer to God. So it was, so that's שמחתי באומרים בית
ה' נלך. samachti be'omrim beis hashem neilech. When people were just saying,
I just want to make עליה לרגל, aliyah leregel, I just wish
דוד David would die, that made me happy because people want to
do
מצוות. אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar lo hakadosh baruch hu, God
said to him, כי טוב יום בחצריך מאלף. ki tov yom bachatzeirecha
me'alef. טוב לי יום אחד שאתה עוסק בתורה לפני מאלף עולות שעתיד
שלמה בנך להקריב על גבי המזבח. tov li yom echad she'ata osek
batorah lifnai me'alef olos she'asid shelomo bincha lehakriv al gabei hamizbe'ach. And
they said to him, you know what דוד, David, that's very nice
that you rejoiced for that, but you should just know that one
day of learning תורה is worth a thousand sacrifices. So don't feel
like maybe דוד David was trying, with his joy, he was covering
up that he was feeling bad also, God said, you know, don't
feel bad, even one day. Okay. I guess we will end here.
I wanted to turn the page, but we will at least, but
this is an ending point. So we will have a little catching
up to do.